[
  {
    "question": "Who is the Hindu god of destruction?",
    "options": [
      "Lord Vishnu",
      "Lord Brahma",
      "Lord Shiva",
      "Lord Ganesh"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Lord Shiva"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the demon king in the Indian epic Ramayana?",
    "options": [
      "Ravana",
      "Kumbhakarna",
      "Meghnad",
      "Maricha"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Ravana"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which goddess is considered the symbol of power and shakti in Hindu mythology?",
    "options": [
      "Goddess Saraswati",
      "Goddess Lakshmi",
      "Goddess Durga",
      "Goddess Parvati"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Goddess Durga"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the eighth avatar of Lord Vishnu in Hindu mythology?",
    "options": [
      "Lord Rama",
      "Lord Krishna",
      "Lord Buddha",
      "Lord Kalki"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Lord Krishna"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the Mahabharata, who was the teacher of the Pandavas and Kauravas?",
    "options": [
      "Sage Vyasa",
      "Sage Narada",
      "Sage Durvasa",
      "Sage Dronacharya"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Sage Dronacharya"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the vehicle (vahana) of Lord Vishnu?",
    "options": [
      "Garuda",
      "Nandi",
      "Hamsa",
      "Peacock"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Garuda"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which demon was granted the boon that he could not be killed by man or animal, day or night?",
    "options": [
      "Hiranyakashipu",
      "Ravana",
      "Mahishasura",
      "Bakasura"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Hiranyakashipu"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the goddess of wealth and prosperity in Hindu mythology?",
    "options": [
      "Goddess Saraswati",
      "Goddess Lakshmi",
      "Goddess Durga",
      "Goddess Parvati"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Goddess Lakshmi"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the Ramayana, who was the younger brother of Lord Rama?",
    "options": [
      "Lakshmana",
      "Bharata",
      "Shatrughna",
      "Hanuman"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Lakshmana"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the monkey god and a devoted follower of Lord Rama in the Ramayana?",
    "options": [
      "Vali",
      "Sugriva",
      "Angada",
      "Jambavan"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Hanuman"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the goddess of knowledge, music, arts, wisdom, and learning?",
    "options": [
      "Goddess Saraswati",
      "Goddess Lakshmi",
      "Goddess Durga",
      "Goddess Parvati"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Goddess Saraswati"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the creator of the universe in Hindu mythology?",
    "options": [
      "Lord Vishnu",
      "Lord Brahma",
      "Lord Shiva",
      "Lord Ganesh"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Lord Brahma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the demon king's sister who tricked Lord Rama by transforming into a golden deer?",
    "options": [
      "Mandodari",
      "Surpanakha",
      "Tadaka",
      "Shurpanakha"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Shurpanakha"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the wife of Lord Shiva and the mother of Lord Ganesha?",
    "options": [
      "Goddess Saraswati",
      "Goddess Lakshmi",
      "Goddess Durga",
      "Goddess Parvati"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Goddess Parvati"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which epic contains the dialogue between Prince Arjuna and Lord Krishna known as the Bhagavad Gita?",
    "options": [
      "Mahabharata",
      "Ramayana",
      "Puranas",
      "Upanishads"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Mahabharata"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the demoness who was slayed by Goddess Durga in a fierce battle?",
    "options": [
      "Simhika",
      "Tadaka",
      "Mahishasura",
      "Shumbha"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Mahishasura"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the wife of Lord Vishnu and is worshipped as the divine mother?",
    "options": [
      "Goddess Saraswati",
      "Goddess Lakshmi",
      "Goddess Durga",
      "Goddess Parvati"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Goddess Lakshmi"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the sage who composed the Hindu epic Ramayana?",
    "options": [
      "Sage Valmiki",
      "Sage Vashishtha",
      "Sage Vishwamitra",
      "Sage Narada"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Sage Valmiki"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the son of Lord Shiva and Goddess Parvati, known for his elephant-like head?",
    "options": [
      "Lord Vishnu",
      "Lord Brahma",
      "Lord Shiva",
      "Lord Ganesh"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Lord Ganesh"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the villainous character in the Mahabharata known for his deceit and cunning nature?",
    "options": [
      "Duryodhana",
      "Karna",
      "Shakuni",
      "Dronacharya"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Shakuni"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which demon was granted the boon that he could not be killed by any weapon?",
    "options": [
      "Ravana",
      "Hiranyakashipu",
      "Mahishasura",
      "Bhasmasura"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Bhasmasura"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the divine cow in Hindu mythology who grants wishes?",
    "options": [
      "Kamadhenu",
      "Surabhi",
      "Nandini",
      "Kamadhuk"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Kamadhenu"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the Mahabharata, who was the teacher of Eklavya?",
    "options": [
      "Sage Vyasa",
      "Sage Narada",
      "Sage Durvasa",
      "Sage Dronacharya"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Sage Dronacharya"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the goddess of time, power, and destruction in Hindu mythology?",
    "options": [
      "Goddess Saraswati",
      "Goddess Lakshmi",
      "Goddess Durga",
      "Goddess Kali"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Goddess Kali"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which prince won the hand of Draupadi in the Mahabharata by performing a difficult archery task?",
    "options": [
      "Arjuna",
      "Bhima",
      "Nakula",
      "Yudhishthira"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Arjuna"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the goddess of learning, wisdom, music, and arts?",
    "options": [
      "Goddess Saraswati",
      "Goddess Lakshmi",
      "Goddess Durga",
      "Goddess Parvati"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Goddess Saraswati"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the king of the monkeys and a loyal friend of Lord Rama in the Ramayana?",
    "options": [
      "Vali",
      "Sugriva",
      "Angada",
      "Jambavan"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Sugriva"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the demoness who was slayed by Lord Rama in the Indian epic Ramayana?",
    "options": [
      "Surpanakha",
      "Tadaka",
      "Simhika",
      "Shurpanakha"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Tadaka"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which god is considered the preserver and protector of the universe in Hindu mythology?",
    "options": [
      "Lord Vishnu",
      "Lord Brahma",
      "Lord Shiva",
      "Lord Ganesh"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Lord Vishnu"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the son of Lord Shiva and Goddess Parvati, known as the god of war?",
    "options": [
      "Lord Vishnu",
      "Lord Brahma",
      "Lord Shiva",
      "Lord Kartikeya"
    ],
    "correct_answer": "Lord Kartikeya"
  }
]
